In today's video we will talk
about critical illness insurance.  Now you might be thinking
that you have taken a health insurance policy.
What is a critical illness insurance policy?  So health insurance
policy covers your hospitalization
expenses.
Health
insurance policy covers any hospitalization related to any condition.  So suppose
if there is any critical illness
like cancer, heart problem,
paralysis.  Any disease which is critical
in nature is diagnosed as a critical illness
and whatever hospital expenses are incurred
after hospitalization, it is
covered by your health insurance policy
and if you have taken a stand alone critical
illness policy, that is, you have
also taken critical illness insurance separately, then the
hospitalization expenses will be
given by the health insurance policy and one time
benefit fixed lump sum benefit will be
given by your critical illness insurance policy.
Therefore both policies are important.  You are seeing
that critical illnesses are increasing.
If you look at 10 years ago and today, you will
see how many people are getting cancer.
How many people are having heart problems,
this rate will keep increasing and the survival
benefit will also increase because of the advancement of
science and technology.  So in that case
also, there will be some expenses which the
health insurance policy will not cover.
Which a lump sum benefit policy can cover us.
When a critical illness occurs, two
things happen.  One thing is that recurring
expenses keep coming.  Secondly, earning
capacity decreases.  So our expenses are the same.
Expenses have increased in fact
but earnings will be less.  So to compensate for that, it
is necessary for us to take a lump sum critical illness policy.  So today we will talk about
which five critical illness
insurance policies you
can consider for your family.
[Music]
Quick reminder before we start the video,
if you haven't already, please subscribe to our channel
so that you get the right
information at the right time.  Let's move on to the video.
Top Five Critical Illness
Insurance Pluses of 2026.  Neema Bhupa
Critical Care Plan, HDFC Ergo Critical
Illness Plan, Aditya Birla Active Secure
Critical Illness Plan, ICICI LBAR Critical
Shield Plan and Bajaj Aleans Critical Care
Plan.  We will compare these five plans
on the basis of features, eligibility
criteria, coverage scope and cost.
So first let us talk about
what is the incurred claim ratio of these companies?  Meaning how much
premium did they collect and how much did they
pay in claims.  The incurred
claim ratio of Neema Bhupa is 61.22%,
HDFC Ago is 84.85%,
Aditya Birla is 71.5%, ICICI LBAT is
82.24%, Bajaj is 87.31%. So, the critical
illness policy is a very specific
policy.  There you get a specific
number of illnesses covered.  Defined
illnesses are covered.  Every policy has a
list of diseases that will be covered.  There is a
list of 20 diseases in NIVAPA and only
these 20 diseases will be covered.
If there are 20 diseases then the sum will be paid.
HDFC Ergo has a list of 15 diseases.
Aditya Birla has three plans.
Plan One lists 20 illnesses, Plan
Two lists 50 illnesses and Plan Three
lists 64 illnesses.
Maximum illnesses covered in ICICI LBA.  There is a list of 92 illnesses
which come under critical illness.
Bajaj Reliance has a list of 43 diseases.
So here is the list of 20 diseases in Nima BP.  It is in
front of you.  If you have any of these 20
diseases, you will be cleared.
Here is the list of 15 from HDFC.   Here is the
list of Aditya Birla's Plan One, Plan Two, Plan Three.   The
coverage scope of ICICI LBA is quite broad.
You will see that 90-92 illnesses are
divided into different buckets.  That list is here in
front of you.  Bajaj Eliyaz
is also divided into different buckets.  Here is their list.
We will also attach these brochures
in the description box of this video.  So that
you can download and refer to this
list.  Illnesses covered by HDFC Ago.
What is the scope of coverage?
What all do you cover?  Heart attack,
multiple sclerosis, stroke, cancer
, organ transplant, coronary artery
disease, bypass surgery, kidney failure and
heart valve replacement are covered.
Even in Aditya Birla Active Secure,
if you are looking at Plan One, 20 illnesses
are specified.  Which ones?  50 illnesses
are also specified and 64 are also specified.
ICSC Labard has a coverage scope.  There
are five buckets.  Such as Cancer and Blood,
Heart and Blood, Major Organs, Nervous
System, Other Illnesses.
92 illnesses are covered in these buckets, the list of which is in front of you.
So the best part here is
what happens in critical illness when you get the
claim.  Suppose
any of these is diagnosed from one bucket then
your policy ends there.  But
ICC LB, unless all five buckets are exhausted, the
policy will not be exhausted.
Your policy will continue.  The five segments in Bajaj CI
are Cancer Care,
Cardiovascular Care, Kidney Care, Neuro
Care, Transplants and Sensory Organ
Care.  So now let us talk about what kind of
claims will be received.  There is a lump sum option in Neevapa.
In the lumpsum option, you will get 100% off
sum assured.  If any of these 20
diseases is diagnosed, then 100% of the sum assured will be
given.  The second option is lumpsum plus
staggered payout.  Meaning we will also give Lamsam one
time.  With that, 10% of sum assured every
year will become income for 5 years.  Some amount was
given in lump sum and some was staggered over the
next 5 years.  If you think I do
n't want money together.  If you want to divide it and take it, then you
can also choose the Lumpsum Plus Target Income option.  HDFC
offers lump sum equal to 100% of sum
assured.  Aditya Birla also has lumpsum payout
equal to 100% of sum assured.  ICICI LAD has the
concept of major illness and minor illness which is defined in the policy.
If the cover for these minor illnesses is 50% and the
cover for major illnesses will be 100%.  Similarly, there
are two categories in Bajaj Reliance.  If the
diagnosis is in category A, then 25%,
in category B, 100%.  Now let's talk about sum assured
options.  There are options ranging from Rs 5 lakh to Rs 2 crore in Neema.
HDFC Ago has an option from Rs 1 lakh to Rs 50
lakh.  Aitya Birla has options ranging from Rs 1 lakh to Rs
1 crore.  ICICI LBAD has an
option from Rs 5 lakh to Rs 40 lakh.  And Bajaj Reliance has
options from Rs 1 lakh to Rs 50 lakh.  And if you have
chosen more than one section from More Than One, then you will get maximum cover of Rs 2 crore only.
Minimum and maximum entry
age.  The minimum entry age in HDFC is 18
years.  Maximum 65 years.  The
minimum entry age for Aditya Birla Plan One and Plan Two is
5 years.  The entry age in Plan 3 is 18 years
and the maximum entry age
in all three plans is 65 years.  In ICICI LBA, one can enter
this policy from 3 months to 65 years.
In Bajaj Reliance also, you can
enter the policy from 3 months to 65 years.
And this dependent child can
continue the policy for 30 years.
All these policies
come with life long reinsurability.  You enter.
After that your policy will
continue for life as long as you are paying the premium.
So now let's talk about the policy type and
how can you take this policy?
How to apply for Individual Family Floater?
Both individual and family floater options are available in Neema Bhupa.
Only individual policies are available at HDFC Argo.
Individual and multi-individual
policies are available at Aditya Birla and
individual and multi-individual policies
are also available at ICICI LBAD.  Individual policy
is available in Bajaj.  Talking about additional benefits,
what add-ons can you add to the
policy? There are no add-ons available in NIBA.
Only the basic inbuilt features are
available.  Add-ons are also not available in HDFC Argo.
Aditya Birla Plus
also does not have any add-ons.
PA which is Personal Accidental Death
Permanent Total Disability and Permanent
Partial Disability along with Cancer
Restore cover is also available in ICIC LBAD.  You can add.  There are
many add ons available in your Bajaj Reliance.  The
first is cancer
reconstructive surgery.  10% of sum assured
maximum Rs 2 lakh is given.  Cardiac
Nursing: If the claim is made under Section
B of Cardiovascular Surgery, 5% of sum
assured up to a maximum of Rs 50,000 will be given if
you have taken this add-on.  Third is
dialysis care.  If the claim is made under
section B of kidney care then 10% of sum
assured up to a maximum of 2 lakhs will be given to you
under dialysis care.  Then there is
physiotherapy care.  If the claim is made
under section B of Neuro.
If given in Neuro then 5% of sum assured maximum Rs
50000.  You can avail additional premium by checking the add-on.
If the claim is made under
Section B of Transplants
and Sensory Neuro Care, then 5% of the sum
assured will be given, maximum Rs 50,000.  This
add on is applicable only when we talked about section B.
We talked about section one and section B
where we talked about 25% and 100%.  If
Section B claim is paid then these add
ons will also be activated.  Initial
waiting period.  So the waiting period is
how long after taking the policy you
cannot make a claim.  If you have
taken a policy in Neevapa then the initial waiting period is
yours.  If you have taken a policy under NIVAPA, then
you cannot claim these critical illnesses for the first 90 days.
If a
policy is accepted for a pre-existing disease, there is a
waiting period of four years for
those PEDs.  HDFC has 90 days.  You have an
initial waiting period of 90 days at Aitya Birla.
ICC LBA also has 90 days.
Bajaj has an initial waiting period of 180 days.
After that there is the survival period.
Some companies have a clause that survival will have to be done.
Meaning, the
claim will be paid only if the person survives for that period of time.   The
survival period of Neema Bhupa is 30 days.   This
means that if someone survives for 30 days after diagnosis, then he
is eligible for critical illness claim.  HDFC Ergo 15 days
to 30 days depending on the illness.  It's Birla
's 15th day.  There
is no survival period for ICIC LBA.  Meaning
you can make a claim as soon as the diagnosis is made.  And Bajaj has a
survival period of 7 to 15 days.
Now let us talk about the common eligibility of everyone as to
who can take this policy as per their income.  The
sum assured can only
go up to 12 to 15 times your income.
You can take sum assured only 12 to 15 times your annual income.  12
Times for Salary and 15 Times for Self
Employed or Business Person.  Earning
up to 12 times for the member.  If there is a non-
earning spouse, then 50% cover is given to you.
Maximum eligibility 30 lt.  This will
depend from policy to policy but these
are some common guidelines.  Non-Earning Parent
Parent in Loss 50% of Proposal Sum Assured.
50% of the proposal sum assured
but maximum ₹1 lakh for children 50% of the
proposal sum assured maximum ₹15 lakh
We have already discussed what will not be covered, what is the
coverage scope, how will it be covered, what is the
initial waiting period, what is the
survival period, there are some things which will
not be covered in your policy, if there is a
critical illness
due to sexually transmitted diseases or HIV AIDS,
if there is any non-disclosure
due to which a critical illness occurs then also you will
not get it, if it occurs due to alcohol and drug abuse then
also you will not get treatment
due to congenital birth, animals, if there was any
congenital problem which was treated
due to which a critical illness occurred then also you will
not get the claim and here
claim will not be given even in natural calamity.
Now let's talk about what is its claim process
?  Meaning if you take a critical illness
policy then there is no cashless claim.
This is a reimbursement claim.
Only after you suffer a critical illness, you have to
intimate the insurance company and
claim the fixed benefit.  So there
is a reimbursement claim.  What
will the process be like?  Completed claim form.  You have to
fill the claim form properly.
It will have all the columns like when was it diagnosed
?  What was the first consultation?  What were the
symptoms that made you go to the doctor
and so on.  Along with this, a medical
certificate is required which will confirm that
you have this critical illness.  Along with this, a
certificate is asked from a doctor
in which he says that the critical illness is
not due to a pre-existing disease.
Meaning it is not related to that.  If it is different from that then
this claim is given.  And
you know that the first 90 days is a waiting period.
So if that problem does not occur in the first 90 days
then the initial waiting period should
qualify.  All your
supplementary medical papers will be required in
photocopies, policy copies will be required.  Your
KYC documents will be required.  PAN, Aadhaar,
KYC documents along with cancelled cheque
where the claim amount will be credited to you.  And if it
is an accidental case then FIR and medical
legal documents will also be required.  This was the basic
information about how to make a claim.
Some specific documents may be
asked for from company to company, policy to policy
, it will depend on case to case.  Now let's talk about
premiums, how much premium will be
charged?  Now here I have taken edge as 35
and sum assured as 25 less.  So
if someone is taking a policy at the age of 25 or 35,
what is his premium as of today?
Neema Bhupa's premium is 8276.  The
premium for Aitya Birla Plan One is Rs 6614.
Plan 2 is 875 and Plan 3 is
10136.  ICICI Lombard has 9500
and Bajaj Reliance has 6348.  So, these were the
details about critical illness plans that are
available in the market.  So, do your due
diligence before taking Critical Illness Plus
and here full disclosure will matter
because this is a fixed benefit
policy and there is a big claim.  There
is a claim for major illness.  So it
is very important to have full disclosure.
You can choose your critical illness plan as per your suitability as per your eligibility.  If you
need any guidance, you
can connect.  Our WhatsApp
number, email ID, calling number from our team is mentioned.   There
is also a Google Form link.  You will fill that.
We will contact you.  And
before we go, a quick reminder, if
you haven't subscribed to our channel yet, please do so.
So that you get the right infection at
the right time.  See you in the next video.  Till then
stay safe, take care.  Bye-bye.